Thank you for being here. We've got Te Reo Reka, who are joining us this morning
for the first
20 minutes. We'd love it if you could just leave some time for questions as well as
part of that. But we've got you for 20 minutes, so over to you.
Great. Thank you. So I think well for me.
I'm Victoria McLaughlin. I am the deputy secretary for
Te Reo Reka and-
Carl Paper, chief operating officer.
So thank you for taking us up on the offer
of doing a demonstration of Te Reo Reka today.
We're doing it as a video
in part to make sure that we could share it easily in this room
and that was technically difficult enough.
The video
takes you a little bit for a snippet of current state and then shows you
how that actually looks like in the solution.
We are on track to go live in late November,
down in Christchurch, Ashburton, and for our
central registry services.
The focus on that launch is on the functionality
for the registry and the judiciary.
And then, in March, we
bring out
the whole solution, including the portal for the profession,
parties to cases, and that will be rolled out to the
remaining parts of the South Island.
And then we progressively move up the island
in April and May. So by the end
at June, we will be rolled out across the country for the
family court.
So on that note, we will demonstrate what the system
looks like.
Great.
For someone needing orders from the family court, the application process can be
complex and stressful. Applicants may need to complete multiple
forms, work out which forms apply to their situation, and enter the same
information repeatedly across different documents.
It can be difficult to know what information is mandatory, what supporting
documents are required, and whether the application has been completed correctly.
Applicants may also need to print forms and visit a courthouse to file their
application.
Instead of navigating multiple paper forms and filing processes, the
courts portal guides an applicant through submitting an online application to the
court. The applicant starts by choosing the application type and filing
method. Based on those selections, the portal presents the relevant fields they
need to complete.
As the applicant moves through the process, the portal provides contextual guidance
to explain what information is required and why.
When an applicant is completing more than one application, data is entered once
and reused across the applications.
For example, children's names and dates of birth.
The information captured on the online forms flows directly through to the
court. This reduces the need for registry staff to reenter
information, improving data accuracy.
For applicants experiencing family violence or other sensitive
situations, the portal includes a quick exit feature that allows users
to leave the application immediately, helping to keep them safe.
Unlike paper-based forms, the courts portal supports better data
quality through field validation, such as checking email address
formats and using the New Zealand Post postcode finder for address
details. Where appropriate, users can override validation if
needed. The navigation panel on the left-hand side of the screen steps the
applicant through the process and guides them to provide the relevant details about
the court order they are seeking. Once the application details are complete, the
applicant can upload supporting documents by navigating to the file or
desktop. The applicant can then declare their
application is true and correct, digitally authenticate it, and submit
it to the court. This replaces the need to physically sign documents and
visit the courthouse. If a filing fee applies, the applicant is prompted
to pay the fee.
Once an application is received, registry staff work through a detailed
manual process before it can be referred to a judge.
They must review all forms and supporting documents, check that all required
information has been provided, and identify and resolve any issues.
They must also search across existing systems for related cases and parties.
Information from the forms then needs to be manually entered into the current
case management system, potentially resulting in data entry errors.
The documents cannot be stored within the system, resulting in the court being
reliant on the physical file. If the application is associated with an
existing case, registry staff need to locate the physical case file.
They then add the new material to that file.
If it is a new matter, the registry must create a new physical case
file. The process is time-consuming, requiring information to be handled
multiple times and involving movement between physical files and the current case
management system.
With the new solution, registry staff have a single dashboard view of all
applications submitted to the court.
When an application is opened, key information is automatically populated
from the courts portal, including party names, application details,
court location, legislation, and application type Registry
staff can then check and confirm the information is correct, reducing
manual effort and minimizing data entry errors.
Once the application meets the acceptance criteria, registry staff can use the
search function to determine whether it should be linked to an existing case or
whether a new case needs to be created.
In this example, no existing case is found, requiring the creation
of a new case file. After the application has been accepted, registry
staff can process any related case documents that were also filed
through the courts portal. From the Acceptance Outcome tab, documents can be
reviewed, edited if required, and accepted together.
The timeline at the top of the screen guides registry staff through the process
and automatically updates to reflect the next stage of the workflow.
The next step is to navigate to the Accepted Application screen and
create the digital case file. Selecting the application prompts a check for
any existing cases. As no matching cases are identified, a new case
is created. The case is named in accordance with existing case title
naming conventions and allocated to the appropriate registry staff
member. Party information supplied through the courts portal is carried
through automatically, enabling the originating application party
profiles to be linked directly to the new case.
Once these steps are completed, the case is created.
All documents filed through the courts portal are automatically added to the
digital case file, removing the need for a physical file.
In this example, Jeanette Jones has requested that her address be kept
confidential. A confidential address flag is created in the Notes and Flags
section and linked to the relevant party.
This indicates that the confidential address must only be used when
communicating directly with that person and must not appear on
correspondence that may be viewed by other parties.
The flag is then visible on the case file.
The matter is now ready to be referred to a
judge.
Judges often need to work through large volumes of information.
In the family court, cases can exist from birth through to the age of 18,
resulting in extensive records and several boxes of documents.
Sometimes a document is not on the file, and the registry needs to spend time
locating where it has gone. To prepare making a decision, judge reviews registry
notes, loads relevant documents, and considers previous case information.
Important information is often flagged using handwritten notes, tabs,
or sticky notes to help navigate the material and keep track of key
issues. Once a decision has been made, either in chambers or in a
courtroom, judges record their decisions and outcomes in a minute.
The information then needs to be entered into the current case management system
by registry staff.
Once the case event has been assigned to a judge, it can be selected from the
judicial workspace and opened through the event overview.
The judge can view event notes created by the registry together with important
information relevant to the hearing or case.
The judge can then navigate directly to the documents relevant for the decision or
to the full case file. This includes documents filed by parties, as well
as documents identified by the registry as relevant to the case.
Within each document, the judge can search, highlight, circle key
points, and add comments. These annotations are personal to the judge
and are not visible to others unless the judge chooses to share them.
Once the judge has reviewed the relevant information, they can record the reasons
for their decision. The judge can then record each order or direction they are
issuing. The solution only displays the decision options
associated with that type of application.
For example, they may direct that a directions conference be
allocated. They may also appoint a lawyer for child.
These decisions automatically generate tasks for registry staff to
complete. Directions that relate to case parties, such as filing further
evidence or completing a required task, will also be visible to
verified courts portal users. Before completing the decision,
the judge previews what has been captured and checks the details.
They can edit the decision from the preview screen or return to the previous
screen to make further changes. Once satisfied, the judge authenticates the
decision. Authentication generates the relevant minute, which is then
available for the registry to issue to case parties.
The decision details also generate the relevant next steps.
Once a judge has made a decision, registry staff manually review the
directions and work through the required next steps.
They prepare and issue documents, update case records,
create follow-up tasks, arrange future events, and
notify the parties involved. Staff often need to move between multiple
screens, documents, and processes to ensure nothing is missed
and the case continues to progress.
With the new solution, once a judicial decision has been made, the related
tasks are automatically generated and flow through to the registry for
action. For example, a task may be created to appoint a lawyer for
child. Priorities are automatically assigned so that the most important
work is completed first. The relevant document, such as a judicial
minute, becomes immediately visible to the registry.
The registry can then release the document, and parties are notified through the
courts portal if they have a verified account.
After a decision has been issued, court users are typically notified by
email or letter. If they want more information about the outcome, upcoming
events, or any actions they need to take, they may need to contact the court
directly. Registry staff spend time responding to inquiries, sending documents, and
ensuring parties receive information they need.
They also need time preparing for the next judicial event by checking whether
parties have completed required actions.
Currently, this can be difficult, resulting in delays and adjournments.
With the new courts portal, users receive a notification when a judicial
decision is released. From there, they can view new notifications,
messages, and priority tasks. Users can view their case and access
documents filed with and issued by the court, including judicial
minutes and other case management documents such as notices of event.
Event details can be viewed within the Events section.
If a task or direction has been assigned to a case party, it will be displayed
within the Tasks section. This is just the beginning of a modern, connected
court experience.
Superb. That's it?
That is it.
Fantastic. Well, I can't say I've ever seen a presentation to a
select committee quite like it, but I quite enjoyed it.
I quite enjoyed it, so thank you.
Thank you.
Do you have any other comments you'd like to make before we go to questions?
No, I think we'll open up to questions.
Great, we'll start with Todd Stevenson.
Yeah. Just I've got three, if that's okay, Mr.
Chair, and hopefully they're not too long.
Nobody else chomping at the bit.
No, I am.
First, yeah, obviously, great, thanks for the demonstration.
Very smart doing a video because then there's no problems world and the
electronic world. Or is it only new matters going forward?
Yeah, so-
That's my first question
... that's a very good question. So that's what we refer to as coexistence.
Yeah
The existence of-
Okay
... so it's only new cases that will be
managed in Te Reo on day one.
In March, we open up the ability to move
cases from our old world into the new world.
That's not so much to do with the data.
Its issue is our, as you saw, our current case file
is paper, and therefore getting the correct documents
from there into the solution requires
scanning and effort on the registry.
So that is why we are cautious in how we move between that
world and this one. There are some connections between the two
solutions as well to reduce things like searching,
being able to schedule from both solutions and not have them conflict.
But all the other parts of the process will require a level of
coexistence.
Okay, just two other quick ones.
Just kind of an access to justice question.
Mm-hmm.
Not everyone obviously has a computer, et cetera.
One, will you be making terminals available at court
registries for people to do filing, or are there still paper forms that
they would then be-
Yeah
... done for, that part is kind of done for you.
Yes.
So, yeah.
So the only people that the portal is mandatory for is the
professional.
Right.
Everyone else can still file through the other
means because of that point around access to justice.
So yes, we can balance it, and then we scan those documents in and enter
it into the solution.
And then very last one, Mr. Chair -
Yeah
... if that's okay.
The other thing that kind of occurs to me is over time you'll have really
great data.
Mm-hmm.
So you'd actually see if a matter hasn't...
You could run metrics and see if matters aren't moving forward or-
Yes
... is that your plan? Because again, I
get a lot of feedback, shall we say, about the
length of time, and I know we're obviously trying to speed up the court processes,
but sometimes I'm assuming matters could,
just for whatever reason, aren't progressed.
Yeah.
You've got to run a thing over to say, "Well, why isn't this happening?" A few
months or something.
Yeah. So that's all part of it. So we now will have the
ability to create dashboards, reporting,
that sort of court management
information.
Yeah.
And I think the good thing is the judge will be able to see where the delay is.
So at the moment, the judge doesn't automatically see where a delay is.
There might
be an application for adjournment, and a lawyer might say, "These are the
reasons why I need that." Whereas the judge will be able to track the case
through the system.
Yeah.
So if I step forward a little bit and talk to the criminal space, the
judge will be able to see when the police file disclosure documents.
Yes.
Versus any argy-bargy about who, what, wherever else, and people get
reminders, and a judge will be able to make sure people are held to account,
particularly in that type of space, about being on time.
Yeah. Thank you.
It's a lot more difficult in the manual system.
Great. We've got five more minutes and we've got quite a few questions, so we'll
see what we can do. Greg.
Yeah, thank you.
For this to succeed, how much buy-in will there need to be by the judiciary
and by those others that own a lot of this
information?
Mm-hmm.
The judiciary are notorious for their lack of IT
buy-in. Have been in the past. Things improved a little.
If they continue with that reluctance, will this thing work?
So we're very lucky. This is done in partnership with the
judiciary. Has been since the beginning.
So they're part of the governance, they were part of the selection
process for tool. They have been intimately involved in
the design of what you saw for the judges.
The judges are now demoing it to each other and are supporting the
training. So,
no, there's been a lot of good support because they have been so intimately
involved in its design, which is different from
how it's been treated overseas, where it's been done by
a program to the judiciary. So no, we're very-
Is it all the courts?
Yes. So as we do each phase,
the reference groups change to reflect that
jurisdiction.
Raymond.
Thank you. Mr. Chair, thank you.
Training. This is going to be a big job with training.
I'm
assuming some training has already started or what's training going to look
like for the registry staff?
Do you want to cover or do you want me?
Yeah, no, that's fine. So it was two parts.
So,
as the member has talked about, we are doing capability uplift in general.
With the judiciary, there is training going on at the moment for the judiciary just
to lift the capability where that's needed.
From a personal perspective, I'm not IT literate 100%, so I'd probably be
taking advantage of that. So that's going on at the moment from a judicial
perspective and where necessary from a staffing perspective, but that's probably a
lesser thing. Training specific to this, there are different
mechanisms that we'll use for this.
We'll have staff involved in user acceptance testing, so staff have helped build
this and staff will test it. So for example, for the Christchurch rollout, there'll
be Christchurch staff testing the system, which will
reduce the need for them to have any training because they would have been already
playing in it for a number of weeks.
So there'll be user staff involved in user acceptance testing, then there'll be
modules and face-to-face sessions for the staff to
get them up to speed. I wouldn't sit here and say it won't be
a little bit bumpy as everybody gets used to a new system.
It's a big, complex court system. That's a great video,
but the Family Court is much bigger than what that 10 minutes
actually shows, and all of the different fields and applications are significant.
But the staff-
Yeah
... are pretty competent, and they'll be able to manage this really well.
Thank you. Are there more questions?
Yes, but you can have one more.
Just look, the big question mark would be on a lot of people's minds, how are we
working around, God forbid, any security breaches?
Because a lot more information is going in. Yes.
So no, we are certainly taking that very, very seriously.
And it's partly why the portal is in March rather than
in November as we work through that.
Next one sort of closed
And we are constantly reconsidering that, with the
comments around AI and how that's changing the cyber threats.
So no, that is being taken very, very seriously, and it's a core part of the
design. Penetration testing, all those elements will be done
as part of approval to go live. Thank you.
Dan Widd.
I've had a little bit of input into the MB biometric upgrade,
right. So I've had a look at some not particularly good management of
IT projects. Have you got a project dashboard for this?
Yes, we do.
Have you got all green lights?
No.
What have you got? What have you got here?
So we do have things that are tracking at amber
around making sure...
In the reporting space,
there's some delays in testing, et cetera.
But they're all things that have management controls in place,
and we are still on track for the November date.
One of the things that came out in that other department was
that
the oversight was kind of at the third level in the
organization,
and the deputy secs didn't really have good
knowledge. Who has ownership of this project?
Okay. So from a governance perspective, we have
both
Andrew as our
Chief Executive over us, and from the judicial side, the Chief Justice.
Sitting under that true governance layer is a
SLT-based steering group. It's got an independent
chair, Colin McDonald. Over it, we have an independent
advisor from Australia who's done a similar program.
SLT is a weekly item on our SLT
agenda alongside it. So it's very much governed at our
executive level.
But ultimately,
are you the owner of the project?
I am the owner, and this is my only job.
Good. And my last question is, we saw-
Sorry, just... And I'm the business owner.
Right.
So because ultimately Victoria's leading a project that's
delivering a tool for the services that I do, so I have
a lot of time and effort spent on this as well.
And this is my last question, I think. Forgive my suspicion.
But
the video was really slick.
Could I get
online now or onto the system now and do
all of those things we saw?
Yes. The only thing that you couldn't do right at the moment is that
dashboard at the end in the portal.
That's currently being built out.
But all the other parts are actually under active testing.
But yeah. And we are still building out the portal at the moment for that March
release. But what you were seeing was not a-
It wasn't fake.
No, it wasn't fake.
No, it wasn't.
To give you a sense of where we are right now, we have done what's called
integration testing. We are about to go into user acceptance
testing in two weeks. We have been doing mini user
testing for a number of months now.
So we are well into that testing space.
Thank you.
Fantastic. Well, thank you very much for your time-
Thank you
... and for the effort you've put in as well, and we wish you all the best with the
project-
Thank you
... as you move forward